Maine Acadian Cultural Survey Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Graphic materials, The original materials are stored at Ft. Meade.
  - Color slides, 2380 color slides
    - Acadian Festival Parade, Madawaska, Maine, June 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C033; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the annual parade held as part of the Acadian Festival. See MAP-DW-031 for more information; 1-14, The Marching Owls, Madawaska High School band; this band is a source of great pride in the community; 15-16, Baton twirlers; 17-18, Banner of the Sirois/Duplessis family reunion; this was the family whose reunion was a featured event at this year's Festival; 19-20, Mindy Jessica Sirois, youngest family member in attendance at the reunion.
    - Acadian Festival Parade, Madawaska, Maine, June 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C034; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the annual parade held as a part of the Acadian Festival. See MAP-DW-C031 for more information; 1, Late 1950s or early 1960s vintage Cadillac at the head of a group of antique cars; 2-5, Float with representatives of the Sirois/Duplessis family, whose reunion was a featured event at this year's festival; 6, Float sponsored by local supermarkets; 7, Youngsters in t-shirts with environmental message; 8, Victoria Pipe Band; 9-10, Float with members of the Bouchard family, whose reunion was a featured event at the 1990 Acadian Festival; 11-13, Float sponsored by the Caribou Grizzlies; 14-15, Youth band on float sponsored by local PTA; 16-19, Anah Temple Oriental Band from Bangor, ME; 20, Antique fire engine.
    - Acadian Festival parade, Madawaska, Maine; Mount Carmel Catholic Church, Lille, Maine, June 29, 1991 - July 03, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C035; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the annual parade held as a part of the Acadian Festival. See MAP-DW-C031 for more information; 1, Antique fire engine; 2-3, Remote control fire hydrant run by Madawaska fireman; 4, Unknown float; possibly 4-H club; 5, Marcher clad in potato costume; potatoes are the single most important crop in the study area; 6-9, The Keystone Kops, a local organization which participates in a variety of events; 10, Float sponsored by local snowmobile club; 11, Unknown float; 12, Truck carrying advertisement for local business, quite popular with the kids because they were giving away candy; 13-14, Truck carrying Santa Claus (in June!!) who threw candy to the crowd; 15, A nun converses with members of the Sirois/Duplessis family inside the Multi-Purpose Building, which is where the post-parade awards and Festival closing ceremonies took place; The following images document Our Lady of Mt. Carmel Catholic Church in Lille, ME. The church is not part of a currently active parish, and is in the process of being restored by Don Cyr of Lille; 16-18, Hand made tapestry; 19-20, View of an altar; this is not in the main sanctuary.
    - Mount Carmel Catholic Church, Lille, Maine; Camps of Acadia, Eagle Lake, Maine, July 03, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C036; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Mt. Carmel Catholic Church and presbytery in Lille, ME. The church is not part of an active parish, but is being restored by Don Cyr of Lille, who lives in the presbytery; 1, Detail of handmade flower on silk banner; 2, Large cabinet called a vestiare. which holds the various objects and elements used in the services; 3, Elaborately decorated tabernacle; 4-5, Interior of the sanctuary; note the marbleizing on the columns and the statues of the apostles in the high archways; 6, Altar stone; 7, Vestiare; see #2; 8-9, Container for holy water; 10-11, Statue of Our Lady of Mt. Carmel; 12-13, Statue of an apostle; 14-15, Marbleized columns; 16-18, Decorative woodwork on presbytery; These images were taken at the Camps of Acadia on the south shore of Eagle Lake; 19, Cabin; 20, Sign at entrance to camp.
    - Buildings and scenes, Upper St. John River Valley, area, Maine, July 05, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C037; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      A variety of miscellaneous scenes in the study area; 1, Abandoned dairy bar at Eagle Lake; 2, A building in Eagle Lake, perhaps a former fire house; 3-4, Motorized canoe on Eagle Lake; 5, Farmland in the eastern part of Fort Kent; 6, Twilight on Eagle Lake, as seen from the deck of the camp occupied by fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and David Whitman; 7, See #5; 8-9, Abandoned agricultural equipment; a large number of farmers in the study area have quit farming; 10, Spraying in the potato fields; 11, Foundation stone of early church in Lille with crosses carved into it; 12-15, Downtown Fort Kent on July 4th weekend; more flags in evidence than usual, and a patriotic message at the gas station; 16, New pickup truck at a car dealer in Fort Kent; the bright blue/green color is popular on houses; 17-19, Flag on a rock by the Fish River in Fort Kent; white building in the background is an abandoned starch factory; 20, Dock at Eagle Lake Marina; pontoon craft is a commercial tour boat preparing to depart.
    - Old Mill Marina, Eagle Lake, Maine; Lavertu family reunion, Lavertu Settlement, Maine, July 05, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C038; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      A variety of scenes in Eagle Lake; 1-2, Commercial tour boat preparing to leave; 3, A speedboat leaves the dock; 4, Swimming beach at Eagle Lake; 5, Tour boat; 6-7, Old Mill Marina, a former sawmill converted into a motel, restaurant, and marina; 8, Tents set up at Eagle Lake for the annual July 4th parish celebration; 9, A local farmer on his tractor; These images document a reunion of the Lavertu family, held at Lavertu Settlement; there was a barbecue, entertainment, and the unveiling of a monument to the original Lavertu settlers of the area; 10-11, Barn where the barbecue was held, memorabilia was displayed, and souvenirs were sold; the brightly colored t-shirts were made for the reunion; 12-13, The house and a shed on the Lavertu farm; note the gray and red color combination, which is scene on many buildings in the study area; 14-15, Jaguar with Connecticut plates; many people came from out of state to attend the reunion, and most families in the study area have relatives in Connecticut; 16-17, Children in a cart being pulled behind a tractor; Miscellaneous images; 18, A family of loons in Eagle Lake; loons were present on the lake throughout our stay; 19, Knights of Columbus Hall in Fort Kent; 20, Shed with gambrel roof; this roof style is used on many different buildings in the study area, including barns, houses, commercial buildings, and sheds. Some of the sheds appear to have been built from kits, and some from scratch.
    - Variety of buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine, July 10, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C039; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and other scenes in Fort Kent; 1-3, A variety of buildings showing the use of the gambrel roof in different contexts; this roof style is widely used in the study area; 4, Decorative eagles on a home; the use of the eagle as a decorative motif is quite common; 5, Ten commandments on a trailer; 6, Decorative eagle on a garage; 7, Many mailboxes are set back to allow for the buildup of snow; 8, Decorative eagle on a carport; 9, Looking north across the St. John River at agricultural land in New Brunswick; 10, House painted in vivid blue/green shade, a common color choice; 11, Another common color used on buildings, a red-brown that could be called oxblood; also note the use of the gambrel roof; 12, A common type of structure behind houses, meant to hold firewood; 13, Another set back mailbox; 14, Mobile home with bright blue/green paint; 15, Mobile home with added roof using gambrel style; 16, Set back mailbox with reflector added to warn snowplow; 17, Barn or garage with gambrel roof; 18, House with bright blue trim; 19, House and shed painted in gray and red; 20, House painted bright blue/green.
    - Buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine; Shrines, churches, homes, Frenchville, Maine, July 10, 1991 - July 11, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C040; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      Some miscellaneous buildings and scenes in Fort Kent; 1, House painted bright blue/green, a common color choice; 2, Shrine in a yard; a great number of houses in the study area have such shrines, primarily to the Virgin Mary; 3-4, Decorative eagles on a house; eagles are often used as a decorative motif; 5, Another shrine, this one is in front of an apartment; 6, Bright colors are used in a variety of settings, here as painted rocks by a driveway; 7-8, Gambrel-roofed shed; St. Louis Catholic Church is in the background; 9-12, A type of wheeled dock locally called a quay (or quai); the wheels allow the dock to be removed from the water before it freezes, thus averting ice damage. These are common on lakes in the study area; this one is on Eagle Lake; 13-20, Wooden strip canoe being built by Jerry White and Mark Jallbert at White's home in Frenchville.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine, July 12, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C041; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes in Fort Kent, ME; 1-2, Alberie Pelletier works in some of his potato fields; 3-4, A potato house of the type located near the railroad tracks which served to store potatoes prior to shipment; this particular example, located on Market St., has been converted to retail shops; 5, A beauty salon in a house; combining business and home is a common occurrence, and beauty salons are particularly well represented in this category; 6, Shrine in the yard; many houses in the study area have such shrines; 7, Decorative eagle on a house, a motif seen throughout the study area; 8, Mailboxes are often buried by snow or hit by snowplows; residents have tried to solve the problem by setting the boxes back off the road; 9-10, A type of rectangular clothesline seen throughout the study area; 11, House painted a bright blue/green; similar colors are seen on many houses; 12, Another set-back mailbox; the supporting structure, according to fieldworker Ray Brassieur, resembles a type of trap called a figure 4; 13-14, Wildflowers, which were plentiful in the study area in June and July; 15-16, Alberie Pelletier in his potato field; 17-18, House and shed painted bright blue; the gambrel roof on the shed is a style used on a variety of buildings; 19-20, Farmland in eastern Fort Kent, on North Perley Brook Rd.; small herds of cattle are found occasionally on farms in the study area.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine, July 12, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C042; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of scenes in Fort Kent; 1-2, Farmland; part of the land currently forested was probably once agricultural; 3, An interesting road sign; 4, Small herds of livestock are occasionally seen on farms in the study area; 5, House painted in a gray and red color scheme; this color combination is found throughout the study area; 6-14, Wildflowers contribute a great deal to the scenic beauty of the area; 15-16, Mailboxes are often buried by snow or hit by snowplows; setting them back off the road helps solve the problem; 17, House painted a bright blue/green; many houses in the study area are painted with similar shades; 18-19, A type of rectangular clothesline common in the area; 20, Truck at Tardiff sawmill.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine;, July 12, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C043; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes in Fort Kent; 1, Tardiff sawmill on the Fish River; 2-3, Two similar houses on State Highway 11. The smaller sections are probably additions; such lateral additions are one of the most common types in the study area; 4, House painted bright blue, a common color choice; 5, House with lateral addition; 6, Replica of Eiffel Tower, said to be built by the resident of the house; 7, Decorative eagle on house; eagles are commonly used as a decoration; 8, See #6; 9, Another house with a lateral addition; 10, Shed with a gambrel roof, a style used on a variety of buildings in the study area; 11, A vegetable garden; 12, Farmland as seen from State Highway 11; the hedgerows running up the hill may mark lines of original property division; 13, Shrine at the end of a driveway; 14, Beauty salon in a house on State Highway 11; the incorporation of business and residence is common; 15-16, Wheeled docks, locally called quay for email; the wheels enable the docks to be pulled from the water before the winter freeze, thus averting ice damage; 17, Two houses which use colors commonly seen in the study area— bright blue/green and gray and red; 18, Decorative butterflies on a house; these are seen throughout the study area, but a concentration of them is on State Highway 11 between Fort Kent and Eagle Lake; not surprisingly, there is a maker of the butterflies on this road; 19, Another example of a residence/business combination, this one an auto repair shop; 20, A house with a lateral addition.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine, and Wallagrass, Maine, July 12, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C044; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1, Decorative eagle on house; 2, Abandoned and collapsing barn; many farmers in the area have quit farming, and abandoned agricultural buildings are found throughout the study area; 3-4, Decorative butterflies; see #18; 5, Decorative eagle; 6, The Saucier Store on State Highway 11. The combination of house and store common; there are three such stores along the twelve mile stretch of Highway 11 between Eagle Lake and Fort Kent; 7, Mailbox set back from road to avoid snow and snowplow damage; 8, Rectangular clothesline, a type common in the area; 9-11, Collapsing farm buildings; 12-13, Eagle Lake as seen from a hill on State Highway 11; much of the land now forested was at one time agricultural; 14, House incorporating gambrel roofline as a decorative element; 15, Wildflowers; 16, Farm buildings no longer in use; 17, Another rectangular clothesline; most are made with wooden posts, but these are metal; 18, Decorative butterflies, made from a wide variety of scrap wood (including leftover paneling) and hand-painted are seen on houses throughout the study area; a maker of the butterflies (name unknown) lives in this house; 19, A beauty salon in a residence; a number of these can be found in the study area; 20, Logging truck parked at a house on State Highway 11; independent trucking is an occupation of importance in the study area.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Wallagrass, Maine; Eagle Lake, Maine; Madawaska, Maine, July 13, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C045; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1-2, Wooden "running potato" in a yard; this is a fairly common type of yard ornament; 3, Sign at Aroostook Creations, a craft shop on State Highway 11; 4, Rectangular clothesline, a common type in the area; 5, House with a lateral addition; this type of addition is one of the most common types in the study area; 6, Forest and grassland; some of this was probably once farmland; 7, An abandoned house along a stream west of State Highway 11. The materials used indicate that this was built in the 20th century, but birch bark was still used as insulation; 8, A wheeled dock (quay); the wheels enable the dock to be pulled from the water before the winter freeze, thus averting ice damage; 9, Looking east toward Brown's Point from the west side of Eagle Lake; the gray and red house of Katherine Brown is visible, as is the red house belonging to Phil Brown which served as home to fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and David Whitman during the survey; 10, Quay; see #8; 11, An island in Eagle Lake; 12, Quay; see #8; 13, See #9; 14, House of Fort Kent artist George Roy; 15, Shrine at a house in Fort Kent; many houses in the study area have such shrines; 6, 16 Windmill made by George Roy, who claims it can generate electricity if properly hooked up; 17, Artist George Roy with a chainsaw carving which he made; 18, Potato fields and a small herd of cattle on a farm along U.S. Route 1 in Frenchville; 19-20, Downtown Madawaska at night.
    - Main Street, Madawaska, Maine; Forever Young Club; Shrine on U.S. Hwy 1, Frenchville, Maine; Tintamarre at Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine, July 13, 1991 - July 14, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C046; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      1-2, Main St., downtown Madawaska at night; 3, Looking in at the Forever Young Club from the parking lot during a Saturday night dance; 4, Shrine at a house on U.S. Highway 1; these shrines are common at houses in the study area, but only a few are lit at night like this one; These images document an event called Tintamarre, which was held during the annual Grande Riviere Festival in Van Buren. A Tintamarre is apparently some type of celebratory noisemaking; at this event, Americans contested against Canadians to see which side could make the most noise; 5-20, People gather in parking lots prior to a procession to the international bridge between Van Buren, ME, and StLeonard, New Brunswick, the site of the contest. The assorted pots, pans, washboards, etc., are used for noisemaking.
    - Tintamarre, Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine, July 14, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C047; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Tintamarre at the annual Grande Riviere Festival. See MAP-DW-C046 for more information; 1-5, People gather in parking lots with their noisemaking devices prior to the procession to the international bridge; 6-15, The procession begins; smaller groups of people from various lots and street corners join as the larger group passes by; 16-19, The procession passes by the U.S. Customs Service building and on to the international bridge to meet the Canadian noisemakers; 20, Canadians on the bridge for the noisemaking contest.
    - Tintamarre and tug-of-war, Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine; Bridge in Saint-Lenoard, New Brunswick, July 14, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C048; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Tintamarre and the tug-of war at the annual Grande Riviere Festival. See MAP-DW-C046 for more information; 1-7, The Canadian noisemaking delegation on the international bridge; 8, Judges announce the winners— the Canadians. The man with the bullhorn is the mayor of Ste-Ouenne, France; a group from that town visits each year to take part in the Grande Riviere Festival. Early settlers of the Van Buren— Ste-Leonard area, at one time called Grande Riviere, were from Ste-Ouenne; 9, Looking up the St. John River from the international bridge; a canoe can be seen on the river, but in general boating on the St. John was uncommon; 10, Various dignitaries address the crowd; 11, Canoe on the St. John; 12-13, See #10; 14, View of the international bridge from the Maine side; 15-20, International tug-of-war, Van Buren v. St-Leonard, on the bridge; incredibly, traffic was allowed to pass despite the crowd of participants and spectators, and it seemed a dangerous situation.
    - International tug-of-war, Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine; Farrell-Michaud house, Van Buren, Maine; Moose at sawmill, Wallagrass, Maine, July 14, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C049; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document an international tug-of-war, Van Buren v. StLeonard, on the international bridge, an event in the annual Grande Riviere Festival; 1, Looking down the rope at the Canadian team; 2, Canadian team pulls; 3-4, Contest over— Canadians are victorious; 5-9, Traffic continued to pass over the bridge throughout the tug-of-war, despite a large crowd of participants and spectators; 10-14, The Farrell-Michaud house, early 20th century construction, on the National Register of Historic Places, currently operating as a bed-and-breakfast; 15, Sign at the Farrell-Michaud house; 16-20, Only confirmed moose sighting, at a sawmill on State Highway 11 in Wallagrass.
    - Moose at sawmill, Wallagrass, Maine; Various buildings and scenes, New Canada, Maine, July 14, 1991 - July 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C050; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of scenes; 1-2, Only confirmed moose sighting, at a sawmill in Wallagrass; 3, Sign on barn on potato farm in Soldier Pond; customized signs are found on most of the farms in the study area; 4-7, Potato fields in blossom, New Canada; 8, Garage with a type of facade normally associated with a commercial building, where the facade carries some type of message; many buildings in the study area which seem to be associated only with residential property have such facades; 9-10, See #4-7; 11-13, Close-up of potato blossoms; 14-15, See #8; particularly perplexing is the facade in #15, which faces away from the road; 16, Forest and grassland, New Canada; 17, Typical partially buried potato house; 18, Fieldworker David Whitman's truck is up to its axles in weeds; 19, Wildflowers, a variety of which contribute greatly to the scenic beauty of the area; 20, Abandoned agricultural equipment; the number of farms in the study area has greatly diminished in the last twenty years.
    - Various buildings and scenes, New Canada, Fort Kent, and Van Buren, Maine, July 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C051; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of scenes throughout the study area; 1, Abandoned farm equipment; see MAP-DW-C051, #20; 2, Mailbox set back from the road to avoid damage by snow and snowplow; 3, Typical partially buried potato house; this one is no longer in use, a common occurrence; 4, Many residents have some type of cottage industry in which they operate from their homes; 5, Building with facade; see MAP-DW-C050, #8; 6, Rectangular clothesline, a commonly seen type; 7, Small barn with gambrel roof, a style used on a wide variety of buildings in the study area; 8-9, A variety of trucks parked at homes along State Highway 161; independent trucking, sometimes combined with farming, is an important occupation in the region; 10, Small herds of livestock are only occasionally seen on farms in the study area; 11, Custom sign with MPG (Maine Potato Growers) logo; such sings are seen on many farms; 12, Farmstead on State Highway 161; 13, Another independent trucker (see #8-9); 14, Another custom sign on a potato farm; note that this one specifically mentions trucking (see #8-9); 15, Non-commercial building with facade; see MAP-DW-C050, #8; 16-18, Spraying the potato fields; potato farming is said to be quite input intensive; 19, Another farming/trucking custom sign on a potato farm, this one is south of Van Buren on U.S. Highway 1; 20, Looking east from U.S. 1, south of Van Buren; the peak in the distance is probably in New Brunswick.
    - Native American Day, Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine, July 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C052; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides